Adrian Valente

ML Research Scientist & Engineer, PhD

About me

Engineer and scientist, I combine a research mindset with rigorous software/ML engineering practice. I have worked on ML applied to biology for 6 years in academia and industry but amopen to other fields of application

Skills

Python shell R
C++
Java C#

pytorch pandas JAX/flax
HF git SQL

Human Languages

French (Native) Spanish (Native) English (Fluent, TOEFL 108)

Personal Information

Citizenship: French Residence: Paris Born 1995 Driving License

Teaching

Explainable AI (PSL, 2023) Statistics (SciencesPo, 2021-23) Python & DS (ENS, 2019-22)



adrian.valente@ens.fr



adrian-valente.github.io



adrian-valente

EXPERIENCE

Since 05/2024

Research Engineer

INSTADEEP · Paris, FR

LLMs for mRNA technology. Developed new generative models, evaluation suites, and contributed to customer projects (fine-tuning)

Technologies: jax, pytorch, huggingface, GCP (& TPUs)

06/2023-05/2024

Research Scientist

ERVIMMUNE · Lyon, FR

ML models to identify targets for novel cancer vaccines, using proteomic and transcriptomic data; set-up of a dedicated HPC cluster for the company;

Technologies: python, pytorch, slurm, snakemake, (sc)RNA-seq

2022-2023 2019-2022

Postdoc

PhD Student

Ecole Normale Superieure · Paris, FR

Deep learning applied to neuroscience, with emphasis on interpretability. Published 4 papers (3 as first, 300+ citations), 8 abstracts, 2 open-source projects, 8 technical blog posts. Teached several classes and supervised interns and early PhD students. Technologies: python, pytorch, slurm, electrophysiology.

08/2018-02/2019

Software Engineering Intern

MICROSOFT · Paris, FR

Development and deployment of back-end software and anomaly detection algorithms for the Universal Store.

Technologies: C#, Scope (U-SQL), Azure.

EDUCATION

2019–2023 **ENS Paris**

PhD, Computational Neuroscience

2017-2019 **EPFL**

Master in Computer Science

2nd best GPA

2014-2017 **Ecole Polytechnique**

Engineering Diploma, Applied maths & CS

2012-2014 Classes prepa

Lycee Stanislas.

Undergrad studies in maths & physics

SELECTED PROJECTS

- hippoLLM: hybrid graph-vector storage system for LLMs (python, langchain). [Code][Abstract]
- Low-rank RNNs for neuroscience (python, pytorch). [Code] [Blog]
- Technical blog on ML & statistics, e.g. the new wave of RNNs. [Link]
- Labs on explainable AI for master classes [Github]

PUBLICATIONS

- **2022** <u>Valente</u> A., Pillow J., Ostojic S., "Extracting computational mechanisms from neural data using low-rank RNNs", *NeurIPS 2022*, link.
- **2022** Dubreuil* A., <u>Valente</u>* A., Beiran M., Mastrogiuseppe F., Ostojic S., "The role of population structure in computations through neural dynamics", *Nature Neuroscience*, 25, p. 783-794, link
- **Valente** A., Ostojic S., Pillow J., "Probing the Relationship Between Latent Linear Dynamical Systems and Low-Rank Recurrent Neural Network Models", *Neural Computation*, 34(9), p. 1871 1893 link
- **2021** Beiran M., Dubreuil A., <u>Valente</u> A., Mastrogiuseppe F., Ostojic S., "Shaping dynamics with multiple populations in low-rank recurrent networks", *Neural Computation*, 33(6), p. 1572-1615, link.